let's say you're trying to find some
solid information about a serious health
problem that concerns you high blood
pressure
diabetes yet everywhere you look
someone's trying to sell you something
like vitamins yoga mats blenders drugs
well breathe a s relief because all we
bring you are the facts welcome to the
nutrition facts podcast I'm your host Dr
Michael
Gregor live from my treadmill I bring
you answers to wide variety of questions
uh like the benefits of milk thistle a
dietary recommendations for polycystic
ovary syndrome and how to use vinegar to
combat blood sugar
spikes okay let's see what questions we
have for everybody Rocky McFly asked
there is new concern about meat-based
nutrients like ronic acid toine cartin
carnosine in the German vegan community
and some advice to supplement I should
we be worried is our new data okay well
guess what you and I are both meat-based
the reason animals make arachadonic acid
toine cartin carnosine is because
they're animals guess what we're animals
we make it we make all these molecules
we make carnitine we make ronic acid so
there's no reason to supplement it um
unless you're not an animal but you
really are next up oie ask
um is having a high basic metabolic rate
a bad thing does it really mean a
shorter lifespan ah yes the candle that
burns
brighter um Burns
faster um well so I we do have evidence
that slowing metabolic rate does appear
to extend life span um and so how do we
do that slow metabolic rate we can do
that through chloric restriction or my
favorite method through nitrat rich
vegetables so that's dark green leafy
vegetables as well as beats so you can
go around starving all the time or just
eat a big
salad um uh so anyway that that would be
the way to decrease your um metabolic
rate for
longevity um also would I recommend a
good vegan B12 andega supplement
brand um so uh the most important thing
with B12 is to get the right type of B12
cyano cobalamin because the most shelf
stable form um and so buy whatever is
the right dose that's the cheapest
cyanic abalin you can find oh and you
also do want to get kind of a chewable
or a sublingual or a spray or liquid
something like that that dissolves in
your mouth mixes with your
saliva um and so uh whatever you can
find out there I would recommend uh
2,000 micrograms once a week um for
those under 65 and over 65 1,000
micrograms once a day in terms of
Omega-3s um uh I think these days the um
uh the alga based DHA is made by one
company is just labeled with different
brands so it's the same stuff just in
different packaging so again might as
well get cheapest I recommend
considering 250 milligrams of a pluen
free meaning algae based
DHA
um uh in the cheapest form you can buy
it okay and you are absolutely welcome
for all the work that I do next up
is Elena says is red algae a reliable
source of calcium for vegans with
ostosis need additional
supplementation um calcium
supplementation does not help those with
ostero um prosis you just need to have
sufficient calcium effect calcium
supplements aren't um safe they're
neither safe nor effective as I have
videos on both of those going through
the data um but we do need to get
calcium from somewhere well it's the
best source of calcium low oxalate dark
green leafy vegetables there's lots of
sords you can get it from calcium satu
sesame seeds blah blah blah but um um
all dark green leafy vegetables which
the exception of beet green spinach and
swiss chard which are fantastic Foods
just a little uh little stingy with
their calcium um all the other grains
like kale and collar and booy Etc the
best sources um of calcium because of
all the other wonderful nutrients they
have like those vegetable nitrates I
just talked about next up oh Elena is
back again any signs back benefits of
milk thisel milk thisel is a supplement
traditionally used for liver issues the
problem is the way it's harvested for
some reason they have to harvest it
moist uh something to do with the pods
or whatever and when you and whatever
however they harvest it U ends up being
contaminated with mold in fact serious
molds um and so there's these fungal
toxins like apoxin um such that I would
stay away from milk thisal supplements
regardless of what they can do because
they're contaminated with fungal toxins
bu or bow sorry I don't know how to
pronounce people's names bow McFarland
says here are a lot of negative press
the evils of seed oils this include
black humanum seed oil and supplement
why not just eat black human seeds or
ground black cumin seeds just black
cumin seed powder that would be um that
would be preferable but no that's not
what they're talking about with seed
oils they're talking about like cotton
seed oil safflower sunflower these high
Omega 6 Rich oils in the deodorization
process um uh refining oils creates
compounds like 3 mcpd which is bad for
you and so yeah we want to try to
decrease our intake of of refined oils
but um don't have to have any oil at all
and certainly might as well get all the
nutrition in your black Human by eating
it
powdered okay Brandon says do women need
col while pregnant no women make
collagen um in fact we all make collagen
no need to take any in our
mouth deac
says um there was a video suggesting
thousand micrograms of B12 daily over 65
that's what I just said very good
um uh yeah so yeah you can get away with
2500 mrrams a week or even just 2,000
micrograms a week or 50 every day for if
you're under 65 but yeah you really do
need 1 th000 daily um over age
65 that's what you should do uh and cyan
cabalin
fantastic next up Ronin says given that
tofu and most mushrooms must be cooked
um should we treat the utensils that
come in contact with them same way we do
raw meat okay well the reason most
mushrooms need to be cooked has nothing
to do with kind of like a food safety
issue but rather a toxin issue um a
garus mushrooms which are white
mushrooms crey mushrooms or crini
mushrooms and portella mushrooms um are
gicus mushrooms and produce a toxin
called gutin which is destroyed by
cooking so you want to cook those kind
of mushrooms um then you cook shitaki
for a different reason um because they
have H toxin that can cause fagula
dermatitis and then morel mushrooms need
to cook for a different reason there
toxins in that too and also wouldn't
want to eat them with alcohol but other
mushrooms are fine so oyster mushrooms
for example you can totally eat them raw
I've actually started growing oyster
mushrooms one of the reasons one of the
things that came out of how not to age
my research is the importance of uh the
importance of eating fungus importance
of eating mushrooms
and uh fermented fungal fermented foods
like Tempe for ergine and spermine and
all sorts of wonderful things and so I
actually started making oyster mushrooms
sold cool you can do it in your house
just like you can make like
Sprouts um you get fresh produce every
you know during the winter you do the
same thing with oyster mushrooms and you
don't need to cook them
although yeah I eat them cooked because
I like them cooked but anyway um and but
now tofu we do want to not eat raw e
cooked because of concerns about um uh
food safety um bacterial contamination
um but it's not at the kind of level
where you you got to drip a little uh
tofu juice like chicken juice onto your
broccoli and run into run into problems
um and so the answer is
no okay Margaret supp overdue on our
daily consumption of fermented
foods
um uh okay well the the big problem with
fermented foods typically is the sodium
content it's too much salt and something
like sauerkraut there are ways of
fermentation like with Tempe um where
you can ferment foods without the
addition of salt that'd be the best way
to go uh um yeah if you are going to eat
something like Sauer cro make sure to
rinse it underwater to get rid of some
of the excess
sodium Sheila says I want to fast for
autophagy but I have hypothyroidism how
do can I get to the point of autophagy
oh wonderful I got a whole chapter on
autophagy and fasting is just one way to
boost it you can fast or go fast 60
Minutes of moderate to vigorous physical
activity aerobic activity will increase
aagy um as with decreasing your intake
of acrylamide which is found
concentrated in french fries and potato
chips because that inhibits autophagy um
and then we should try to go out of our
way to eat spermine rich foods the
target is 20 milligrams of spermine a
day how do we get that um Tempe
mushrooms peas and wheat germs most
concentrated cheapest source that's
another thing I've changed in my diet
started adding eating wheat germ so now
I mix my wheat germ with my ground flax
seeds half and half uh sprinkle that on
my Foods because I want spermine as an
autophagy inducer and Longevity compound
also drinking coffee coffee induces
autophagy thanks to chlorogenic acid
which is the primary antioxidant in
coffee drinking three cups a day of
regular or Decap increases um
autophagy um um or at least associated
with increased lifespan which we assume
is an autop effect because uh
chlorogenic acid does uh increase utopy
in vitro um as well as um um we can
activate utopy through ampk which is
kind of an anti-aging enzyme and I go
into boosting mpk by eating you know you
know that's where the black human comes
in hibiscus tea and vinegar and
barberries and on down the list as well
as following recommendations to suppress
mour because mtor um which is a kind of
a which is a pro-aging enzyme suppresses
aop
and we decrease Amor by um avoiding
animal protein or reducing our intake
protein General and animal protein in
particular okay what's
next okay Rachel Walford is 24 hopeful
PL based wonderful ah fantastic avoid
High AGS what are AGS they're geronto
toxins they're aging toxins Advanced
glycation M products which are created
um most concentrated forms in high dry
heat cooked meat so boiled excuse me
broiled baked fried grilled meat
produces these agent pro-aging toxins so
if you're going to eat meat steam it
boil it stew it par boil it I don't know
anyway okay but this is not a problem
here with Rachel um does have um
polycystic ovary
syndrome um
and uh oh but her blood sugar control is
fine as well as her testosterone huh
okay so those are typical pea symptoms
so what do I think of a nasl spearmint
okay spearmint decreases testosterone
but it says your testosterone is fine
unless you've been taking spearmint and
that's why testosterone's fine that's
possible um
umon spon I'm looking through these uh
these various compounds so
uh one is so I'm trying to think do I
have I do have videos on
peos U PCOS I check out my videos on
nutrition facts that or I forgot what my
recommendations were but I do have
dietary
recommendations um maybe mint was one of
them for a decrease in testosterone that
doesn't seem to be your issue um and
these other ones I don't remember them
popping up in the video um although
bourine which you can get from
barberries is an amk booster which which
is one of those anti-aging
Pathways Carolyn says I have balsamic
vinegar seven times a day wonderful to
reduce blood sugar spikes which is one
of the many benefits it's also an mpk
inducer um is it okay daily is there one
type of is this okay and is there one
type of vinegar that's better um so the
magic is in the acetic acid um which is
the definition of vinegar which is water
with which is a dilute solution of
acetic acid so all vinegar
have acetic acid and so choose your
favorite vinegar I mean something like
apple cider vinegar has a few little
apple phytonutrients along with the
acetic acid and balsamic is a few little
grape phytonutrients but uh even plain
white nasty distilled white vinegar
would have um those benefits that you're
talking about um and yeah several times
a day is fine you just don't want to
ever have vinegar straight because you
can burn your
esophagus um but yeah in fact that's one
of my 21 tweaks for weight loss is this
the two teaspoons of vinegar with every
meal all right fantastic good good
job okay Rachel's back saying any advice
in getting rid of angular
kitis I I've never um looked into
lifestyle interventions for that
condition so I'm sorry I can't help
you um do you think it's essential this
Carolyn taking omega-3 subon every day
it's better to have eyes
oh separate question okay um so I think
we should consider taking 250 milligrams
of pollutant free algae based DHA every
day yes is it better to have iodine from
seaweed or supplements um well I mean
you can take it for supplement um uh I
mean you can get iodine
from I mean iodine is found a variety of
crops it's just it depends on what the
iodine content of the soil is to depend
on what um uh you know is in your crops
um and you never really know where your
crops are grown so you don't know if it
has enough iodine so yeah get an
concentrated source of iodine like
seaweed so you can like snack on Nory
sheets you know um which convenient way
and a tasty way to get your iodine you
can use k um not kelp um DOL powder
which is very kind of mild seaweed or
araria which is kind of noodle likee um
seaweed and soups and stuff so yeah I'd
encourage people to find a way to eat
sea vegetables um but yeah you could
supplement particularly important for
pregnant women to have a regular
reliable source of iodine so you know
150 micrograms few times a week is all
you
need
okay what are my thoughts on the health
benefits of berberine well um if you're
getting from barberries that sounds good
so barberries are sh of berberine
barberries are these little tart berries
you can find in Middle Eastern Grocers
because they use they make a Persian
rice dish out of it but I just sprinkle
it on everything because they're
delicious in fact H I'm actually out I
got to make myself a I was just looking
for them um I got to order some more
barberries um uh and so uh yeah but I do
think there's a caution for pregnant and
breastfeeding women with barberries um
because of the Burber rine so that'd be
my only caution on that point I would
not take it as supplement I would get it
from a whole food source okay Jeff
suggesting for landing a plant-based
industry job in Southern California oh
how fun well hey if anybody has a
job talk to
Jeff um I don't is there like some kind
of plant-based board like I know I like
some of the healthc
Care uh in the healthcare Arena I know
but I don't know in the non-healthcare
arena so uh I'm sorry I don't
know um the best place for industry job
board if anybody knows a plant-based
industry job board let me know so we can
tell Jeff about it
okay Sheila says oh I'm a male carrier
my dad was a male carrier that's awesome
and well working the Heat and sweat a
lot salt still not advised you should be
able to get all the soda you need from
food um no need to take salt or salt
supplements how Jeff is back saying how
do I how do my opinions differ or agree
with the following doctor's opinions or
recommendations Dr dugall spelled wrong
um heavy potato and storage diet Dr
eston wow spelled right that's the tough
one to spell avoiding uh nuts and oil
even olive oil um so I uh I
agree 99% with both of those doctors um
in fact I just saw Dr M speak at the
international plant-based nutrition
Healthcare conference it was arousing oh
in fact I think it's free on plantrician
website
um they gave him a luminary award well
deserved um and so he encourages to eat
starchy Foods fruits vegetables and
starchy foods like beans and um whole
grains I couldn't agree more um my uh we
probably differ on uh white potatoes I'd
rather people see people eat sweet
potatoes and white potatoes just because
they're um have uh you know more
nutrition but uh that's not much to
argue over
um he also I think is skeptical of my
vitamin D recommendation um for people
getting inadequate Sun um he's not a big
fan of Vitamin D
supplements um I talk about and he's
actually right in terms of all cause
mortality but uh still decreases cancer
mortality and so if you're not going to
get heart disease because you're eating
a healthy plant-based diet then cancer
is probably your number one Nemesis and
so maybe vitamin
D3 um would extend life spans and those
who aren't worrying about cardiovascular
disease as much still an unanswered
question but I would suggest that's
possible Sandy is in
Canada I'm going to be speaking in
Canada uh I forget when but it's part of
my tour um oh cannot find um a chewable
sublingual or liquid B12 and sonan
Balman um you can't get online I just
ordered an online oh yeah you get it in
TBL form you could chew those uh yeah so
you want it to mix with saliva ideally
for maximum absorption so I guess you
could chew like a regular B12 tablet
although I can't uh promise it'll be
tasty but I don't even like the flavored
ones I wish they just make on the
flavorless but they have like raspberry
or some cherry flavor something gross
like that anyway next up do I recommend
yearly doctor visits s weh you know I
actually talk about uh I actually have a
video about annual doctor visits and how
we don't have um evidence to show that's
beneficial um uh but
uh um yeah so it depends at you know
what age you're certain um you know you
want to make sure that you're getting
your cholesterol followed to make sure
it's low enough and you know at age 50
there's recommendations for or or at age
45 there's recommendations for coloral
cancer screening age 50 recommendations
for shingles vaccine age 65
recommendations for or a pneumonia
vaccine so there certainly are some
landmarks um where um um you would need
medical care but there's not great
evidence suggesting that annual medical
um follow-ups are useful unless they're
actually giving unless you have a
lifestyle medicine doctor who's actually
inspiring you to eat healthier to move
more to stop smoking you know um if you
had a doctor that talks you about all
that stuff and you left that off as
being like Oh I'm gonna exercise more
and I'm gonna eat heal healthier and you
know oh my God now that's the kind of
doctor viness that could save your
life
yeah I don't know how likely that is
that your doctor's like that Johnny says
I suffered a stroke oh God I'm so sorry
age 36 now on warer auman for life hav
been diagnosed with antios pholin yeah
cling syndrome um I'm already on hopeful
Plum B St do I have any particular
suggestions on what to eat so you stay
on warfriend for your life period um and
because warer and works thins your blood
by interfering with um the action of
vitamin K you need to keep your vitamin
K intake steady to kind of match your
warring dose um and so if all of the
sudden one day you were just like
binging on lots of dark green leafy
vegetables with lots of vitamin K then
you could impair the ability of that
drug to thin your blood so want you to
eat lots of greens but you just have to
eat lots of greens on a regular basis
and so they can match your Warr level to
kind of effectively block that much
vitamin K in your
diet okay next up
Alexander uh wants to know if I
recommend a protein intake yeah oh I do
re I do recommend a protein intake 0.8
grams per healthy kilogram body weight
um according to this do I have to decide
whether my goal is longevity or
bodybuilding that's totally up to you
certainly for um elderly individuals
there's no benefit to additional protein
supplements um on top of adequate um
protein in terms of muscle mass muscle
strength or muscle
performance we would love it if you
could share with us your stories about
Reinventing Your Health through
evidence-based nutrition good
nutritionfacts.org testimonials we may
be able to share it on social media to
help Inspire others
if you'd like to see any graphs charts
Graphics images or studies mentioned
here go to the nutrition facts podcast
landing page there you'll find all the
detailed information you need plus links
to all the sources we site for each of
these topics my last two books were how
to survive a pandemic and my how not to
diet cookbook get ready this year for
the launch of how not to age and of
course all the proceeds for the sales of
all my books goes directly to charity
nutrition fact .org is a nonprofit
science-based Public Service where you
can sign up for free daily updates on
the latest in nutrition research with
bite-sized videos and articles uploaded
nearly every day everything on the
website is free there are no ads no
corporate sponsorships no Kickbacks is
strictly non-commercial not selling
anything I just put it up as a public
service as a labor of love as a tribute
to my grandmother whose own life was
saved with evidence-based
nutrition